<tool id="asp" name="ASP" version="0.3">
	<description>Accurate splice site prediction</description>
	<command interpreter="bash">./asp.sh
		$fasta_input
		$organism
		$result_format
		$spf_gff
		$spf_spf
		$acc_spf_binary.extra_files_path
		$acc_spf_binary
		$don_spf_binary.extra_files_path
		$don_spf_binary
		$sigmoid_transform
		> $log_file
	</command>
	<inputs>
		<param format="fasta" name="fasta_input" type="data" label="Genome sequence in FASTA format" help=""/>
		<param name="organism" type="select" label="Organism" help="">
			<option value="Cress">Arabidopsis thaliana</option>
		        <option value="Worm">Caenorhabditis elegans</option>
		        <option value="Fly">Drosophila melanogaster</option>
		        <option value="Human">Homo sapiens</option>
		        <option value="Fish">Danio rerio</option>
		</param>
		<param name="sigmoid_transform" type="select" label="Use sigmoid-transform on SVM outputs to obtain score between 0 and 1" help="By default it is Yes.">
			<option value="yes">Yes</option>
			<option value="no">No</option>
		</param>
		<param name="result_format" type="select" label="Prediction result file format" help="Types of file format available for prediction results.">
			<option value="gff2">GFF (Version 2)</option>
			<option value="spf1">ASCII SPF (Version 1)</option>
			<option value="binary">SPF format (binary format compatible with Palmapper and QPALMA)</option>
		</param>
	</inputs>
	<outputs>
		<data format="gff" name="spf_gff" label="Splice site signal predictions in GFF format">
			<filter>result_format=="gff2"</filter>
		</data>
		<data format="spf" name="spf_spf" label="Splice site signal predictions in SPF format">
			<filter>result_format=="spf1"</filter>
		</data>
		<data format="spf" name="acc_spf_binary" label="Acceptor splice site signal predictions in binary SPF format">
			<filter>result_format=="binary"</filter>
		</data>
		<data format="spf" name="don_spf_binary" label="Donor splice site signal predictions in binary SPF format">
			<filter>result_format=="binary"</filter>
		</data>
		<data format="txt" name="log_file" label="Log File">
			<filter>result_format=="binary"</filter>
		</data>
	</outputs>
  <help>

**What it does**

ASP_ predicts splice sites on genomic sequences of several species [1].

It takes a genomic sequence in FASTA format and for every position
that exhibits a splice site consensus dimer (AG for acceptor splice
sites, GT/GC for donor splice site) computes a score indicating how
likely the position is a splice site.  ASP uses a window of 141 nt
around each position. Therefore, there are no predictions near the
boundaries. Predictions are performed on the forward and backward
strand for all sequences in the FASTA file.

.. _ASP: http://www.fml.tuebingen.mpg.de/raetsch/suppl/splice

**References:**

[1] Soeren Sonnenburg, Gabriele Schweikert, Petra Philips, Jonas Behr, and Gunnar Raetsch: Accurate splice site prediction using support vector machines, BMC Bioinformatics 2007, 8(Suppl 10):S7.

------

**Output:**

The output is a file in GFF-like format which contains a prediction
score for each candidate location in the genomic input sequence.

Each line contains the sequence name, the position in the sequence,
the information about which kind of splice site type (GT/GC/AG) is
considered and the SVM score. The GT and GC lines correspond to donor
splice site predictions (consensus sequence is either GT or GC). For
lines with AG, the line corresponds to acceptor splice site
predictions (AG consensus). The score is related to the likelihood
that a the given position is a splice site. The larger the score, the
more likely that there is a splice site. Scores above -1 (original SVM
scores) and above 0.7 (with sigmoid transformation) are quite likely
splice sites.

The tool `SignalPredict` in the `mGene.web modules` section can also
predict splice sites for several organisms. Here the score is
appropriately transformed into a posterior probability that there is a
splice site at the predicted sites. These probabilities are easier to
interpret than the raw SVM outputs provided by ASP.

--------

.. class:: infomark

**About formats**

**SPF format** Signal Prediction format was designed for providing
information such as labels or predictions for specific genomic
locations (with strand information). It has requires exactly six
fields::

    1. chrom - The name of the chromosome (e.g. chr1, chrY_random).
    2. signalName - possible choices include tss, tis, acc, don, cdsStop, cleave.
    3. scoreName - possible choices include label, output, Conf, Conf_Cum
    4. chromPos - The position in the chromosome. (The first base in a chromosome is numbered 1.)
    5. strand - Defines the strand - either '+' or '-'.
    6. score - The score between -infinity and infinity. If scoreName is 'label', then the score should be either -1 or 1.

</help>
</tool>
